NZ permanent resident Auckland University trained Registered NZ teacher

mel.eaton.address@gmail.com (021) 1927774 www.mel-eaton.online-resumes.nz



During my teaching career I have proven my ability to inspire a broad range of students, instilling an appreciation for creativity and promoting 'outside-of-the-box' thinking. I have maintained high standards of achievement, consistently setting the bar for excellence.

# 1 AM...

- An extremely effective communicator
- Friendly and approachable
- Ambitious and enthusiastically optimistic
- Details focused with high standards
- Flexible, easily tackling the unexpected
- Creative, innovative and a problem solver
- Self motivated and showing initiative
- A team player, providing valued support

# KEY EDUCATIONAL SKILLS

- Curriculum development
  Varied assessment
- Confident leadership
  Differentiated learning

- Strong subject knowledge
- Proficient with ICT
- Experienced budget holder
  Extracurricular activities
  Innovative lesson delivery

# ACCOMPLISHMENT HIGHLIGHTS

- As HOD I established and built a new art department to cater to year 7–13 students
- I have hugely benefited from a wealth of travel and international experience
- Founded and managed my own business, a successful arts and crafts centre
- · Training in web development has proven that I am able to reinvent myself with confidence
- In my first year of teaching Film and Media I had students take second place in the Youth International Silent Film Festival and two other groups ranks in the top 10

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE - SUMMARY

Contemporary Maori Art & Film and Media Teacher Tauranga Girls' College Tauranga, New Zealand

(October 2015 – December 2016)

Digital Producer Reserve Group Tauranga, New Zealand

(January 2015 – October 2015)

Founder and Manager Inspiration Station - Art and Craft Centre Doha, Qatar

(June 2013 - April 2014)

Head of Secondary Art and Design Park House English School Doha, Qatar

(September 2007 - June 2013)

Art and Design Technology Teacher **Qatar International School** Doha, Qatar

(January - June 2007)

Art, Design and Art History Teacher Saint Kentigern College Auckland, New Zealand

# EDUCATION AND TRAINING

YOOBEE School of Design Web Development Training (2014)

University of Auckland Graduate Diploma of Teaching (Secondary) (2005)

Bachelor of Fine Arts (2001-2004) Major in Sculpture Minor in Art History

For more details on my skills and experience please continue reading...



# CURRENT EMPLOYMENT (BREAK AT END OF 2016 FOR MATERNITY LEAVE)

## Contemporary Maori Art & Film and Media

Tauranga Girls' College (October 2015 - December 2016) Tauranga (www.tgc.school.nz)

#### Nga Toi and Contemporary Maori Art

The focus of these classes is on developing understanding, appreciation and artistic expression of Maori culture. Use of Te Reo, karakia, contemporary Maori artist models and Maori cultural concepts are of upmost importance. To enhance my relationship with students and as part of my professional development I worked on learning conversational Te Reo. During the year I studied level 2 Te Reo at Te Wanaga O Aotearoa. Unfortunately I was unable to complete the course due to my pregnancy but I am planning on picking up where I left as soon as possible.

#### Film and Media Production

In this subject students produced video work for a range of purposes and contexts - promotional videos for the school, short films and video art installation inspired by artists like Bill Viola and Tony Oursler. The aim of the course is to develop technical skills, such as camera control, editing skills, sound engineering and lighting, as well as scripting, storyboarding and planning/managing a production project.

Last year I was very proud to see two of our girls win second place in the International Youth Silent Film Festival. They were invited to Portland and visited America for the festival and workshops in June.

### Classes I taught were:

- Year 9 and 10 Nga Toi
- Level 1 and 2 Contemporary Maori Art (Painting)
- Level 2 and 3 Film and Media Production

# WEB DEVELOPMENT

Never one to rest on my laurels, and always looking to challenge myself, I took the opportunity in 2014 to extend my training and completed an intensive 12 week course in front end web development at YOOBEE school of design. This was an exciting challenge that opened up my design skills to a whole new industry.



Coding with up to date practice of responsive web design for desktop and mobile devices



Using photoshop to create assets for web including animations

# **Digital Producer**

Reserve Group (January 2015 - October 2015) Tauranga







HTML5

Javascript

Reserve Group is a marketing and consultancy company dealing with mostly tourism clients.

#### My responsibilities included:

- Web development Coding responsive websites for a range of clients using semantically correct and up to date code.
- Liaising with clients Managing client expectations and keeping customers updated on project progress.
- **Project management** Allocating hours for tasks and managing staff members involved in projects to ensure work is delivered on time and within budget.
- **SEO implementation and reporting** Updating and improving websites to ensure quality performance. Reporting to customers on work that has been implemented along with analysis of analytics data.
- Training Very early into the role I was used to train new staff in SEO implementation and reporting.







# ACCOMPLISHMENT HIGHLIGHT

# **Founder and Manager**

Inspiration Station - Art and Craft Centre (June 20 Doha, Qatar

(June 2013 - April 2014)

I believe my work managing Inspiration Station has extended a variety of skills that make me an extremely valuable asset to both your school and community.

I founded a multi-function Art and Craft centre in Doha, Qatar offering a wide range of creative activities and classes for adults and children. Inspiration Station opened in September 2013 and rapidly grew in popularity. To see it flourish was hugely rewarding.

### My role as manager included:

- Design and creation of space I was in charge of designing the allocation of space as well as furnishing to create a functional and creative facility.
- Marketing I employed targeted marketing (such as developing contacts with newspapers and magazines, promoting with local schools and community groups and networking and marketing online) as well as creating a distinct brand identity.
- **Graphic designer** I extended my graphic skills and familiarity with Adobe software when creating all of our branding and promotion material.
- Social media and online presence As part of our marketing I set up and maintained various social network accounts and built our website.
- Events I organised and hosted a number of events at Inspiration Station, from custom birthday parties to larger handcraft markets.
- Administration I set up an online registration system for all of our classes and managed all administration for the centre, including a calendar of events, emailing/ phoning customers, promotions and more.
- Managing budget I maintained the centre's budget when purchasing materials, taking class fees etc.
- Sourcing and managing resources Obtaining materials in Qatar is easier said than done. Searching, negotiation and ingenuity is involved when stocking for class activities.
- Creating and teaching lessons I have thoroughly enjoyed creating exciting and rewarding lesson plans for a range of ages, abilities and interests.
- Managing staff As the business grew I added and managed more tutors.

# BUILDING A COMMUNITY

As manager of Inspiration Station I was also involved in developing a handmade community group called QatART. As a committee board member I was charged with various resposibilities such as administrating the groups finances, organising events, generating publicity material and liasing with members.







# TEACHING EXPERTENCE

#### Head of Secondary Art and Design

Park House English School (September, 2007 – June 2013) Doha, Qatar (www.parkhouseschool.com)

Park House is a co-education international school with a student body of children from countries all around the globe.

## Key responsibilities included:

- Curriculum development
- Leadership
- Budget holder
- Varied assessment
- Informed Reporting
- · Differentiated learning
- Strong subject knowledge
- · Proficient with ICT
- Innovative lesson delivery

#### Classes I taught were:

- British Curriculum Key Stage 3 Art and Design Technology (Year 7 to 9)
- IGCSE Art and Design (Year 10 and 11)
- AS Level Art and Design (Year 12)
- A Level Art and Design (Year 13)
- AS Level Photography (Year 12)

# Art and Design Technology Teacher

Qatar International School (Jan - June, 2007) Doha, Qatar (www.qis.org)

QIS is an international school with a separate sex junior school and mix classes at senior level. I worked here for a period of 6 months, completing the academic year.

#### Classes I taught were:

- Year 7, 8 and 9 Art
- IGCSE Art and Design (Year 10 and 11)
- Year 7, 8 and 9 DT focus on graphic design drawing

# Art, Design and Art History Teacher

Saint Kentigern College (2006) Auckland, New Zealand (www.saintkentigern.com)

At SKC, where each student is issued a laptop, I learned to make best use of new technologies available to better teach my students and manage resources.

# Classes I taught were:

- Level 3 Art History
- Level 2 Design
- Level 1 Art
- Year 10 Art

# OTHER RELEVANT EXPERIENCE

**Graphic/Digital design** - I am familiar with Adobe Photoshop, Illustrator, After Effects and InDesign for producing a variety of graphic design work. I have employed these skills in teaching as well as commissioned work. I am also qualified in web development.



**Yearbook** - At PHES I established the school annual yearbook and published five issues. I aso worked on producing the school yearbook at Tauranga Girls' College. This has involved managing staff submitting content, producing page layouts and coordinating with printers and sponsors.

**Drama** - I have been involved in several school productions designing sets and costumes and leading teams of students to create these. I enjoy being part of the school's wider creative culture.

**Form Tutor** - I have been form tutor to a number of form groups over the years providing pastoral care to students in years 7 to 10.

**Extracurricular activities** - I have led several different extracurricular activities including photography club, school magazine, after school art group and mural painting activities.



# MY TEACHTNG PHTLOSOPHY

As a universal language art manifests itself in the world around us in so many ways. I believe developing visual literacy is incredibly important and will help open up a wealth of opportunities to students.

Investigating art is a gateway to understanding the human condition, where we came from, and how we function. Understanding art not only gives students another way of connecting with the world around them, but also helps them to see their world in multiple dimensions and perspectives. This also develops appreciation for good design, both successful in form and function.

I am particularly interested in the cross-pollination between the traditional definitions of fine arts, handmade crafts, performance, moving image and digital work and aim to help student expand their own definitions of what creativity and art can be.

I believe it is not what you do in life but how you do it that is important. Art and design requires a unique way of working and thinking. I hope to open and expose students, from all playing fields, to the diversity of creative expression to be found in any arena of imagination.

My goal is to encourage innovative thinking and an awareness of learning through creative investigation — to provide students with the information, resources, and encouragement to ask the right questions, chase the inspiration, and come up with the big ideas. I want to develop and encourage the importance of creative thought that can then be turned into inspired action.

#### ABOUT ME

By definition I am a TCK (Third Culture Kid). I have lived in and travelled to many places across the globe, but New Zealand is the place I call home. I was born in Scotland and briefly lived in the Caribbean whilst immigrating to New Zealand where my family settled in 1995. My accent battles with dual nationality and I am often mistaken for Canadian, which makes for an interesting conversation point. On top of that I have benefited from being part of an expatriate community in Qatar, Middle East, since 2007.

I believe my international experience contributes to my friendly, outgoing, and ambitious personality. I enjoy a challenge and seize every opportunity that crosses my path.



D.O.B. - 22/10/1982

The melting pot of experiences and influences I have enjoyed has also impacted my artistic interests. My eclectic tastes, from the masters of Art History to trends in pop culture, from fine arts to handmade crafts are shaped by my intrepid exploration of new horizons.

I am passionate about creativity in all of its shapes and forms. Most of all I am passionate about fostering creativity in others. I love teaching and sharing ideas and feel privileged to have been able to do so much of what I love in my career so far.

#### PERSONAL INTERESTS AND EXPERIENCE

**Travel** – I consider myself incredibly lucky to have benefited from a wealth of travel experience that has only whetted my appetite for more. I have fulfilled a dream to visit some of the worlds major art galleries such as Moma in New York, the Louvre in Paris, the Uffizi in Florence and more. I feel that all of this adds to life experience that helps me to become a better teacher.

'Jack of all trades' – I have a growing collection of skills, feeling equally confident behind a sewing machine, easel, computer or band saw, and I'm always keen to learn more. I think it is important, especially when working in a practical and creative subject, to remain a student and always learn new techniques for producing work.

**Animation and Moving Image** – When I left secondary school there were two career paths ahead of me - animation and teaching. I love the path I have chosen but I still dream about animation .